Andrés C. Rodríguez, PhD

Stefano-Franscini-Platz 5 HIL D 52.4\$ Zurich, 8093 (+41) 76 595 7722 \$ andrescamilor (at) gmail.com https://ac-rodriguez.co/ \$ Google-Scholar



PROFILE

I am a software developer specialized on **satellite image analysis** with **machine learning** models. I have several years of experience developing machine learning models with business partners on a project basis. My scientific publications showcase: (1) models that can deal with small and biased training datasets; (2) how to design **cost-saving labelling schemes** for large datasets, and (3) early use-cases of **generative models**. I am a **co-founder** of Kapok.ai, a start-up focused on machine learning models for agriculture and ESG sectors.

EXPERIENCE

Kapok.ai

Co-founder, Chief Technology & Architect Officer

April 2022 - September 2023

Zurich, Switzerland

- · Developed crop yield forecasting product with > 90% accuracy, with satellite images as inputs
- · Developed environmental monitoring of deforestation and prototypes of biodiversity monitoring
- · Strategy and product development, customer acquisition and financial and resource planning
- · Presentation and negotiation for funding with Innosuisse projects and VC
- · Product and prototype development with Python, Pytorch, AWS and Dash

ETH Zurich

October 2017 - September 2022

Zurich, Switzerland

Research Assistant

- · Teaching Assistant Image Processing, Machine Learning and Multivariate Statistics
- · Developed tool for mapping of more than 2 billion palm oil trees in south-east Asia with open access data.
- · Supervisor of several thesis and coordination of programming workflows. Relevant topics: Uncertainty estimation, deforestation detection and crop cocoa mapping
- · Co-organizer of several academic and social events in Machine Learning and social media coordinator

Pontificia Universidad Javeriana

March 2014 - July 2016

Research Assistant

Boqota, Colombia

- · Joint Research Project with University of Washington, WA and Northeastern University, MA
- · Data processing and statistical analysis

Jose A Impresores (Lithography)

Project Leader

February 2013 - February 2014

Boqota, Colombia

· Project Management on Process Engineering, Data workflows with R and SQL for KPIs

EDUCATION

ETH Zurich

October 2017 - September 2022

Zurich, Switzerland

PhD Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing

- · Thesis: "Efficient machine learning for large scale remote sensing and natural world datasets"
- · Main focus: Intersection of Deep Learning / Machine Learning, Computer Vision and Remote Sensing for open issues in Ecology and Agriculture.

ETH Zurich

Msc Statistics

August 2017

Zurich, Switzerland

· Thesis: "Unsupervised Learning: Generative Models for Cosmology"

- · Main focus in Machine Learning and probabilistic and generative models
- · COLFUTURO scholarship for graduate studies funded by the Colombian Government

Pontificia Universidad Javeriana

B.S. Industrial Engineering

 $Bogota,\ Colombia$

December 2012

- · Thesis: "Optimizing the use of the muscles in industrial jobs by rotation schemes"
- · Main focus in the intersection of mathematical modeling in industrial environments
- · Graduated with the best GPA of the program in my cohort
- · Outstanding High school Bachelor Scholarship

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Advanced Knowledge Python, Pytorch, Tensorflow, GDAL, QGIS, R, SAS, STATA, GIT Java, SQL, C++, AWS, GCloud

LANGUAGE SKILLS

English C2

German C2 (Goethe C2 Level Certificate)

Spanish Native Language

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Google-Scholar

- [1] Rodríguez, A. C., D'Aronco, Schindler, K., and Wegner, J. D. Fine-grained species recognition with privileged pooling: Better sample efficiency through supervised attention. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis & Machine Intelligence*, 01 (sep 2023), 1–16.
- [2] RODRÍGUEZ, A. C., D'ARONCO, S., DAUDT, R. C., WEGNER, J. D., AND SCHINDLER, K. Zero-shot bird species recognition by learning from field guides. *Accepted to IEEE/CVF Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV) 2024* (2024).
- [3] RODRÍGUEZ, A. C., D'ARONCO, S., SCHINDLER, K., AND WEGNER, J. D. Mapping oil palm density at country scale: An active learning approach. *Remote Sensing of Environment 261* (2021), 112479.
- [4] Rodríguez, A. C., Daudt, R. C., D'Aronco, S., Schindler, K., and Wegner, J. D. Robust damage estimation of typhoon goni on coconut crops with sentinel-2 imagery. *Remote Sensing 13*, 21 (2021), 4302.
- [5] RODRÍGUEZ, A. C., KACPRZAK, T., LUCCHI, A., AMARA, A., SGIER, R., FLURI, J., HOFMANN, T., AND RÉFRÉGIER, A. Fast cosmic web simulations with generative adversarial networks. *Computational Astrophysics and Cosmology* 5, 1 (Nov 2018), 4.

OTHER SKILLS

Rowing, continuos participation in national and international competitions

Also passionate about crossfit, meditation and biking